Guide to the Naval History Society Collection 1721-1995 (bulk 1781-1936) MS 439
New-York Historical Society
- Series 43. US Mail Steam Ship Company (1848-1868)
  The series consists of letter books (both transcribed and letterpress copies) of Marshall O. Roberts, New York agent for the US Mail Steam Ship Company; logs of ships on voyages between New York and Panama via New Orleans and Havana, and from Panama to California; a checkbook; a provision list; and both blank and completed tickets and contracts for passage aboard various ships on US Mail Steam Ship Company and other companies' vessels on these routes.
  Robert's 1848-1849 and 1848-1850 letter books (Volumes 1 and 2) are indexed by recipients. Some of the logbooks document various commanding officers and multiple journeys back and forth along the same maritime routes between New York and San Francisco. They include details of weather, winds, other vessels passed, and crew actions, but do not otherwise document shipboard life. The provisions list is a preprinted listing of possible foodstuffs and other supplies needed for voyages, with blanks to be filled in with the name of vessel, estimate of passengers and number of days of travel, and the amount of each supply. The checkbook consists predominantly of blank checks; a few have been drawn. The foldered receipts and tickets appear to have been removed from ledger volumes of the same type as the SS Antelope tickets in Volume 9.
  Complete transcontinental railroad travel became possible in 1869 and direct shipping from the Atlantic to the Pacific in 1914 with the completion of the Panama Canal. Before then, travel between New York and the West coast required sailing to the Atlantic coast of Panama (usually with stops en route in New Orleans, Havana, and sometimes Jamaica), transit across the isthmus, followed by the Pacific journey to San Francisco. The Atlantic harbor in Panama was Chagras until 1855, when it was moved to Aspinwall (founded in 1850 and named for railway builder William Aspinwall; renamed Colon in 1890).
  Marshall O. Roberts in 1847 had purchased the contract to provide mail steamships to the US government. He would realize enormous profits from the shipping demands of the California Gold Rush and the Civil War. The US Mail Steam Ship Company operated on the Atlantic coast of the United States, and William H. Aspinwall's Pacific Mail Steamship Company on the Pacific. Transit across the isthmus was by mule, wagon, or foot until 1851 when the Vanderbilt Line opened a route through Nicaragua. In 1855 the isthmus railroad connection was inaugurated.
  The materials are arranged chronologically by material type except for the three logbooks of Georgia, which are grouped together for continuity.
  - Receipts for transportation contracts, North American Steamship Company, Arago, 1867 December 18 - 1868 January 2 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Tickets: Opposition Line of steamers to California (completed): Arago, 1868 January 4 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Transit tickets: Central American Transit Company, San Juan del Norte to San Juan del Sur, 1860s (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Tickets: North American Steamship Company, Central American Transit Company, New York to San Francisco, 1st, 2nd, and 3rd class cabins, 1860s (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Contracts: M.O. Roberts line to New York and the East, 1860s (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Tickets and receipts: Granada, 1850s (Box OS 1, Folder 22)
  - Tickets and receipts: Columbus, 1850s (Box OS 3, Folder 5)
  - Tickets and receipts: Georgia, 1850s (Box OS 3, Folder 6)
  - Tickets and receipts: Isthmus, 1850s (Box OS 3, Folder 7)
  - Tickets and receipts: Ohio, 1850s (Box OS 3, Folder 8)
  - Tickets and receipts: Moses Taylor, 1850s (Box OS 3, Folder 9)
  - Tickets and receipts: Republic, 1850s (Box OS 3, Folder 10)
  - Tickets and receipts: People's Line to California via Nicaragua, 1860s (Box OS 3, Folder 11)
  - Letter book of Marshall O. Roberts, New York agent, 1848 November 30 -1849 October 16 (Volume 1)
  - Letter book of Marshall O Roberts, to New Orleans agents, 1848 November 30 - 1850 July 27 (Volume 2)
  - Letter book of Marshall O. Roberts, 1848 December 11 - 1850 August 3 (Volume 3)
  - Letter book of Marshall O. Roberts, New York agent, principally to James R. Jennings at New Orleans, 1850 August 6 - 1853 September 27 (Volume 4)
  - Logbook I US Mail Steamer Georgia, Lt. D.D. Porter, USN, commanding, 1850 January 29 - July 8 (Volume 5)
  - Logbook II US Mail Steamer Georgia, Lt. D.D. Porter, USN, commanding, 1850 July 14 - 1851 January 11 (Volume 6)
  - Logbook III US Mail Steamer Georgia, Lt. D.D. Porter, USN, commanding, 1851 Jun 11 - July 31 (Volume 7)
  - Logbook Empire City, J.D. Wilson commanding, from New York to Chagres via Jamaica, 1850 April - December (Volume 8)
  - Blank tickets and completed receipts for passage from the Isthmus of Panama to San Francisco in the S. S. Antelope of the U.S. Mail Steamship Company, 1850 July 27-Aug 26 (Volume 9)
  - Blank checks and stubs, US Mail Steam Ship Company, 1851 March 13 - 1853 June 15 (Volume 10)
  - Logbook Empire City, John Leeds commander, from New York to Havana, 1852 January 9 - August 24 (Volume 11)
  - Logbook, USM Steamship Ohio from New York to Aspinwall, 1853 January 20 - 1854 March 29 (Volume 12)
  - Provision Lists of Vessels of the US Mail SS Co., 1854-1855 (Volume 13)
  - Logbook Philadelphia, J.F. Schenk USN commanding, voyage 23, 1855 January 2 - January 18 (Volume 14)
  - Logbook Illinois, H.J. Hartstein commanding, 1855 February 20 - 1856 November 28 (Volume 15)
  - Logbook Moses Taylor, 1858 January 5- 1859 May 26 (Volume 16)
  - Logbook USS St. Louis, 1858 October 7 - 1859 April 28 (Volume 17)
  - Logbook Granada, 1859 May 8 - 1860 October 14 (Volume 18)
  - Receipt book for passage from New York on the US Mail Steamship Georgia, 1850s (Volume 19)
- Series 44. US Navy: Officers' autograph letters signed (undated [before 1910])
  The series consists of a one-volume hand-written index of all the autograph letters signed (ALS) owned by John Sanford Barnes (see Series 3), with details about many of them and his additional annotations in red. Some of the letters are included in his extra-illustrated edition of James Fenimore Cooper's "History of the Navy of the United States" (see Series 11), some in the Miscellaneous Manuscripts of the Naval History Society Collection (see Series 52), and others in various extra-illustrated volumes from the Naval History Society's library now cataloged in the XN classification at New-York Historical Society.
  An undated note in Barnes' hand on the inside cover reads: "The numbers to this record refer to the files in Wooden case. More marked B are bound in Naval History, or in many extra-illustrated books. Many of the last named are not recorded and the "List" is imperfect. The ALS of officers of the Civil War are mainly to be found in the bound volume containing their own account of their services furnished Hamersly for his list of officers - [see Series 25] which I have not had time to detach and file. The list is very incomplete and the quotations from the letters are random paragraphs. It has been my purpose to make a better list, more systematically arranged with more frequent and fuller quotations - but I have had to abandon the project." Barnes's unfulfilled objective appears to have been a complete and annotated catalog of the letters.
  Barnes detailed his collecting interests and activities in a lecture he delivered at the Naval War College in 1902, which was published as "Naval Literature" by Captain John S. Barnes in Proceedings of the United States Naval Institute, volume XXIX, no. 2, whole no. 106, p. 32 (XN E182 .B26).
  - List of officers' autograph letters signed, Undated; before 1910 (Volume 1)
- Series 45. US Navy: Civil War ships (1863)
  The series consists of an alphabet tabbed notebook containing descriptions of ships, including their class, size, and guns handwritten in various unidentified hands. The materials in this collection have been digitized and are available online to on-site researchers and to users affiliated with subscribing institutions via EBSCOhost.
  - Civil War list of ships, 1863 (Volume 1)
- Series 46. William K. Wheeler (1860-1975)
  The series consists of the logbook of Flag Lt. Commander William Knox Wheeler aboard USS Colorado during an expedition to Korea from May 19 to June 25, 1871; contemporary newspaper clippings about the expedition; a one-page document in Chinese; and later materials related to use of the logbook as a primary historical source, including articles based on it.
  The logbook turns over to a scrapbook kept by Wheeler's mother, Mrs. T.H. Wheeler of Delhi, New York, of clippings documenting Lt. Wheeler's correspondence from USS Plymouth published in his hometown newspaper (1860); the rescue of survivors from USS Iroquois (1864); Wheeler's assignment to torpedo duty and subsequent court-martial for refusal to perform manual labor (1873); his death from Bright's disease while at sea aboard steamer Alaska; his burial in Libreville, Africa, and his subsequent disinterment, transportation to the United States, and reburial in Delhi (1876).
  The 20th century materials include articles written about the 1871 expedition and information on acquisition of the logbook. There is 1975 correspondence between Robert L. Robinson, associate professor of history at University of Texas at Houston, and New-York Historical Society librarian James Gregory regarding Robinson's article (which is also included) "Gunboat Diplomacy, 1871: An American Officer in Korea," submitted for publication in Proceedings of the United States Naval Institute. An undated photocopy of pages from "Americans in eastern Asia: A critical study of the United States' policy in the Far East in the 19th century," published in 1922 by Tyler Dennett was clipped to William M. Leary's article, "Our Other War in Korea," published in the Proceedings in 1968. There is also 1975 information from Roger Butterfield, Inc. Antiquarian Booksellers, offering the original diary for sale. Gregory's letter to Robinson indicates that the logbook had been recently acquired at the time of his writing.
  USS Colorado, as flagship for Rear Admiral J. Rodgers' squadron, carried the US Minister to China on a diplomatic mission to Korea in April, 1871, attempting to open Korea to contact as Perry had earlier done in Japan (cf. Series 29). Attacks from shore batteries on two ships of the squadron as it made soundings in the Han River led American forces to begin a punitive expedition. It destroyed the forts and inflicted heavy casualties on the Koreans, with minimal loss of American lives.
  - Clippings: Harper's Weekly, 1871 September 9 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Photocopy: "Americans in Eastern Asia," by Tyler Dennett, pp. 452-453, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "Our Other War in Korea," by William M. Leary, Jr., U.S. Naval Institute Proceedings 94, no. 6: 46-53, 1968 June (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Description of Wheeler logbook for sale, from Roger Butterfield, Inc., antiquarian bookseller, 1975 January 24 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - "Gunboat diplomacy, 1871: An American officer in Korea," by Robert L. Robinson, 1975 September 24 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Document in Chinese, Undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Log book of the Corea expedition, 1860-1871 (Volume 1)
- Series 47. John Ancrum Winslow (1842-1875)
  The series consists of Winslow's letters to his wife Katherine A. Winslow before and after Kearsarge's defeat of CSS Alabama under his command, an early letter from Raphael Semmes and the challenge sent by him as commander of Alabama, copies of orders received, letters received by Winslow from various dignitaries after the victory and some sent to Mrs. Winslow after her husband's death, and a 20th century newspaper clipping describing the discovery of Alabama's wreck.
  Some letters to Mrs. Winslow have been redacted in another hand and/or have had portions excised; some appear to have been previously mounted or stored in an album. A few of the earlier letters to her are fragments and have penciled on them the date "April 25, 1962". One letter (December 13, 1861) is from the Winslows' son Chilton relating his father's injuries and includes a penciled note from his father.
  These materials formed the basis for John M. Ellicott's "The life of John Ancrum Winslow, Rear-Admiral, United States Navy, who commanded the U.S. Steamer "Kearsarge" in her action with the Confederate Cruiser "Alabama"," published in 1902 by G.P. Putnam's Sons. Portions of this collection relating to the Civil War have been digitized and are available to on-site researchers and to users affiliated with subscribing institutions via EBSCOhost.
  John Ancrum Winslow (1811-1873) was appointed midshipman in 1827, served in the Mexican War, and was commissioned commander in 1855. During the Civil War, he first served on the upper Mississippi River. Promoted to captain in 1862, he commanded Kearsarge (1863-1864) in pursuit of Confederate cruisers in Europe. On June 19, 1864, in a celebrated naval engagement, Kearsarge sank the Confederate raider Alabama off Cherbourg, France, where it sank. For his victory Winslow was promoted to commodore and received the thanks of Congress. He later commanded the Gulf Squadron (1866-67), was made rear admiral (1870), and commanded the Pacific Squadron (1870-72).
  Various letters were previously individually housed and described, with date, sender, and abstracts of or quotations from their contents. Those are individually housed and described here; the previous wrappers and descriptions from the collection are grouped together at the end of the series.
  - Letters to Mrs. Winslow, 1842 July 2 - August 24 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letters from Raphael Semmes, then in US Navy Lighthouse Board, 1860 November 15, 1861 January 25 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Letters to Mrs. Winslow, 1861 September 15 - December 13 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Copies of orders received, 1862 January 10, January 21, September 27 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letters to Mrs. Winslow, 1862 May 9 - September 29 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Letters to Mrs. Winslow, 1862 October 9 - 1863 June 19 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Letters to Mrs. Winslow, 1863 July 1 - December 20 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Letters to Mrs. Winslow, 1864 January 1 - August 23 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Captain Semmes' challenge to Captain Winslow, 1864 June 14 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Telegram to Vice Consul of U.S., Cherbourg: "Glorious thanks be to god and Winslow" [signed] Putnam, 1864 June 18 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Letter from U.S. Consul General, Paris, Hon. Wm. Drayton, 1864 June 19 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Letter from Rev. L. Dussaud: "written the day of the battle; minister at Cherbourg offering his services to Admiral Winslow, as chaplain for the sick and wounded", 1864 June 19 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Letter from Hon. J.W. Morse, U.S. Consulate, London, 1864 June 20 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Letter from Charles Francis Adams, U.S. Minister London: "Fine letter of congratulations", 1864 June 21 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Letter from George H. Preble (commander, U.S. Sloop of War "St. Louis"), Cadiz, Spain, on "successful destruction of that pest of our commerce the "Alabama"", 1864 June 21 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Letter from Hon. M.L. Dayton, Jr., U.S. Legation, Paris, 1864 June 23 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Letter from Hon. Thomas H. Dudley, Consul General, Liverpool, 1864 June 24 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Letters to Mrs. Winslow, 1865 June 9 - 1868 February 15 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Power of attorney to Catherine A. Winslow, 1865 December 21 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - From Admiral Thornton: "His farewell letter to Winslow who died Sept. 29, 1873", 1873 August 5 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Letters from Mrs. Admiral Farragut to Mrs. Winslow, speaking of her husband's appreciation of Admiral Winslow's service to his country, 1875 January 25, 26 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Clipping: "Civil War drama under way, 30 fathoms deep," New York Times, 1988 June 28 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Typed transcript: June 20, 1864 letter to Mrs. Winslow after defeat of Alabama; excerpt from Appleton's vol. VI, p. 569, biography of Winslow and description of the engagement, Undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Pencil memoranda by Chilton R. Winslow "(for his mother from bulletin board) that "Kearsarge" had sunk the "Alabama" and description of that action", Undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Wrapper "Private papers belonging to John A. Winslow 1863", "Autograph of Adm. W.", Undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Wrappers and descriptions for individual letters, Undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Wrappers for groups of letters, Undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Series 48. Henry A. Wise (pre-1855-1868)
  The series consists of private and unofficial correspondence received by Henry Augustus Wise during his tenure as head of the Navy's Bureau of Ordnance and Hydrography, manuscripts of books he wrote under the pseudonym Harry Gringo, and correspondence related to the publication of his "Captain Brand" by Harper's Weekly. The letters provide details of the ordering, manufacturing and testing of ordnance, as well as everyday personal introductions and invitations. His correspondents include Percival Drayton, commander of the ironclad Passaic and Superintendent of Ordnance at the New York Navy Yard; R. Aulick, Assistant Chief, Bureau of Ordnance; Commander R.B. Hitchcock; Assistant Secretary of the Navy Gustavus Vasa Fox (see Series 17); Monitor designer John Ericsson (see Series 16); Admiral David Porter, whose 1862 correspondence includes humorous sketches of anthropomorphic armaments; public official Hamilton Fish; and Theodore P. Greene (see Series 24).
  Comments penciled on letters in letter book 10 imply that their publication was planned: "Drayton letters, almost without exception, are well worth printing"; and "Those relating to Navy agents and [.. .] (for example) are very pertinent. They should appear". There is no indication within the series that they were published.
  Henry Augustus Wise (1819-1869) entered the Navy as a midshipman in 1834. During the Mexican War (1846-1848) he saw action in the Gulf of California, and then became an expert on gunnery. When the Civil War began, Wise had to decide between staying in the US Navy and serving his home state of Virginia for the Confederacy. He retained his commission, and among his first duties was the burning of Gosport Navy Yard (Norfolk, VA). After a few months on blockade duty he was assigned to the Bureau of Ordnance and Hydrography, the agency responsible for the Navy's armaments and the shore stations where they were produced and tested. He became acting chief in 1863 and was appointed chief in 1864, which position he held until illness necessitated his resignation in 1868. He died in Naples, Italy, the next year.
  The letters were previously disbound from letter books and numbered for indexing in approximate chronological order. However, there are often numbers missing within a documented range. The folders are arranged in letter book order and the letters within them in order as numbered, which is not always strictly chronological.
  - Manuscript: "Tales for the Marines", Before 1855 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letters from Robert Bonner and John Bonner, Harper's Weekly, New York, 1869 August 20 - 1860 June 20 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Copies of letters to Mr. Bonner, 1860 January 13, January 27 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Manuscript: "Captain Brand of the Schooner 'Centipede'", Undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Wrapper: "Tales for the Marines", Undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Naval History Society descriptions of Wise manuscripts materials, Undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Letter book 1: Index, 2-52, 1862 March 31 - August 8 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Letter book 1: 53-100, 1862 August 10 - December 29 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Letter book 2: 47-100, 1862 May 13 - December 30 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Letter book 2: 101-150, 1862 February 5 - May 28 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Letter book 2: 151-202, 1862 May 4 - December 15 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Letter book 2: 203-261, 1862 June 2 - September 2 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Letter book 3: Index, 1-50, 1863 March 3 - April 14 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Letter book 3: 51-100, 1863 February 20 - July 13 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Letter book 3: 102-160, 1863 February 4 - May 7 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Letter book 3: 161-234, 1863 May 2 - June 30 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Letter book 4: Index, 1-51, 1863 July 2 - September 7 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Letter book 4: 52-102, 1863 September 10 - September 29 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Letter book 4: 103-161, 1863 September 29 - October 31 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Letter book 5: Index, 6 - 54, 1863 August 7 - December 21 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Letter book 5: 55-110, 1863 November 2 - December 29 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Letter book 6: Index, 3-48, 1864 January 1 - January 25 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Letter book 6: 51-100, 1864 January 26 - February 19 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Letter book 6: 101-176, 1864 February 20 - March 31 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Letter book 7: Index, 1-53, 1864 April 1 - May 9 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Letter book 7: 53-101, 1864 May 10 - July 18 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Letter book 7: 102-148, 1864 July 18 - September 17 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Letter book 8: Index, 3-51, 1864 August 1 - September 3 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Letter book 8: 52-89, 1864 September 5 - September 29 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Letter book 9: Index, 1-50, 1864 October 3 - November 9 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Letter book 9: 51-107, 1864 November 10 - December 31 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Letter book 10: 4-69, 1865 January 1 - February 17 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Letter book 10: 71- 129, 1865 February 18 - April 3 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Letter book 11: Index, 1-51, 1865 March 23 - September 15 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Letter book 11: 52-101, 1865 October 5 - December 11 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Letter book 11: 102-126, 1865 December 11 - December 30 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Letter book 12: Index, 1-35, 1866 January 1 - 24 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Letter book 12: 36-87, 1866 January 25 - March 9 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Letter book 12: 88-125, 1866 March 9 - April 25 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Letter book 12: 127 - 175, 1866 April 11 - June 24 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Letter book 13: Index, 1-36, 1866 May 30 - August 28 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Letter book 13: 37-103, 1866 September 1 - 1867 January 27 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Letter book 13: 104-150, 1867 January 30 - April 13 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Letter book 13: 151 - 186, 1867 April 15 - May 31 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Letter book 14: Index, 1-32, 1867 June 1 - July 30 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Letter book 14: 33-71, 1867 July 1 - August 31 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Letter book 14: 72-119, 1867 June 1 - November 27 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Letter book 14: 120-147, 1867 November 26 - December 31 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Letter book 15: Index, 1-54, 1865 June 19 - 1866 July 21 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Letter book 15: 55-97, 1866 July 23 - 1868 February 25 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Letter book 15: 98-132, 1867 October 8, 1868 January 1 - May 17 (Box 4, Folder 18)
- Series 49. Logbooks: U.S. Navy (1799-1928, undated)
  The series consists of original and transcribed log books from US naval vessels, including those under the command of John Paul Jones (see Series 28) and Isaac Hull (see Series 27) (USS Constitution) and from lesser-known ships on routine cruises.
  The Serapis logbook is notable for the variety of uses the volume was put to on the vessel under both British command and after its capture by Jones aboard Bon Homme Richard. It includes lists of officers and men aboard Ariel under the command of Jones, and deserters from Bon Homme Richard; was kept on board Serapis from September 26, 1779, to October 14, 1780; and aboard Queen of France in August and September of 1782. It ends with material transcribed at an unspecified date from Jones's papers on deposit at the Library of Congress as of January 18, 1872.